[music]
[snorts]
>> The Wallace and Gromit stories contain
[music] some of the most emotionally
precise visual storytelling ever put on
screen. But, have you ever stopped to
ask how the creators [music] pull it
off? How are they able to make a lump of
clay with no voice and not even a mouth
communicate emotion this powerfully?
Because it's not just the big emotions
that Nick Park and the Aardman animation
team nail, it's the subtle ones, too.
Like here, where we get to see Gromit
cycling through curiosity,
confusion,
and finally, unease.
Of course, part of the answer lies in
the animation itself. But, Wallace and
Gromit's emotional language is also
deeply cinematic. The lighting, the
framing, the editing, and especially the
music are constantly shaping how we feel
about these characters,
>> [music]
>> and none more so than the silent ones.
>> I've seen less capable comedic [music]
human actors than
Gromit. Do you know what I mean? What he
can do with a a look, I say he or
whatever the 15 people have made him
have that look, is sort of Stan
Laurel-esque, you know? It's
I would say it's approaching genius, if
not actual genius.
>> The animation is what [music] defines
Wallace and Gromit. It's what makes it
so unique and so human, not just because
it's such a brutally long process.
>> In a good week, we might hit a minute of
film.
>> Yeah.
>> And that's good going.
>> Good going.
>> That's sailing. That is cruising.
>> But because by virtue of the characters
being modeled from clay, we can
literally see the fingerprints the
animators leave on them in the final
product. But I want to take a moment to
consider the animation and visual
storytelling around [music] Gromit, the
emotional lens through which every one
of these stories is experienced. What's
so fascinating about Gromit is how
emotionally alive he feels despite
having no dialogue, no mouth
articulation, minimal facial mechanics,
[music] and extremely economical
movement. So, how do they do it? [music]
Well, it comes down to how the animators
leverage one of the most important
facial regions [music] for emotional
recognition.
>> The key area is this area here, and
that's the brow. And that's always been
and always will be [music] clay because
it's just the most expressive medium for
us.
>> Gromit stuck under that door was the
first shot I was doing of him, and I
found it just impossible to get a mouth
on him to to model [music] it on him.
And And I In that moment, I I I also
realized I could move the brow up and
down. And And have him look really kind
of hacked off [music] and um and a bit
miserable. And that that was the birth
of Gromit, basically. I realized I I
don't need a mouth, and [music] he says
everything, as you say, with his eyes.
>> And although this was something [music]
Nick Park discovered intuitively, it
lines up with what emotion recognition
research tells us. When it comes to
reading faces,
>> [music]
>> we rely more on the eye region than the
mouth, especially when it comes to
emotions like sadness, [music]
anger, and fear. That's why we always
know what Gromit is thinking, what he's
feeling, what emotional [music]
transition he's undergoing. The
animation team is constantly
orchestrating our emotional response to
him through this region. Like here where
he goes from a state of anger to one of
sadness through his [music] brow
movement alone. To put this in
perspective, look what happens when I
cover this region up. Suddenly, his
emotional state becomes totally
illegible. We can even dial the
ambiguity up further by removing the
music which is doing a lot of emotional
work here.
But really, Gromit's brow does enough on
its own for us to fully grasp his
emotional state here. And that's why the
filmmakers are always keeping this area
so visible. And not just for Gromit.
[music] They're constantly designing
their lighting, prop use, and costumes
around the preservation of emotional
clarity. The use of noir lighting, for
example, isn't just there to create a
more dramatic atmosphere. It's often
directing our gaze to the brow area,
keeping us emotionally invested.
Elsewhere, precise blocking ensures
we're able to read characters even when
their faces are mostly obstructed. Like
here where despite the newspaper, we can
see frustration turn to sadness when
Wallace fails to recognize Gromit's
birthday. Even Gromit's costumes are
often accommodating for his brow.
[music] For instance, notice here how
the animation team finds a clever way to
remove his hat in order to help us to
access the emotion of this moment.
[music]
>> Gromit's expression all comes from his
brow.
So when you put a hat on him,
there's it's very difficult to to get
the expression.
>> Gromit's fearful and apprehensive
reaction to Noolbot is the most
important thing [music] here. It sets up
his entire distrustful story arc with
the AI gnome. And without the
exaggerated brow work, Gromit's distrust
just wouldn't register as effectively.
And the whole emotional logic of that
subplot weakens. But there's more to
this scene beyond [music] the brow work.
And that's the cinematography and how
well every aspect [music] works to
capture the sense of threat and
intimidation Gromit feels here. There's
more obvious aspects, like the use of
shadow as Nutbot's [music] crate
arrives, which does a lot to communicate
the sense of a looming threat, but it's
the shot compositions that are really
interesting, particularly here, where a
low angle, wider focal length, and
subtle forced perspective technique
stretch the spatial relationships and
exaggerate the crate's scale, giving it
a far heavier, more dominant presence
from Gromit's perspective. The shot is
also composed in a Dutch angle, a
technique often used to create a sense
of psychological instability and unease
in the viewer. The result of all this is
that we're not just seeing what Gromit
sees, but also how he sees it. And the
compositions of every subsequent shot
continue this tone, with each
complementing the animation work by
enhancing [music]
the sense of intimidation and
apprehension in Gromit. We see it in
this high angle framing, which has us
looking down on Gromit as he is engulfed
[music] in shadow, subtly diminishing
him and emphasizing his vulnerability.
We see it in the way the camera zooms
out here and settles into another Dutch
angle, maintaining Gromit's [music]
sense of unsteadiness. I could go on,
but I think you get my point. The
[music] cinematography in Wallace and
Gromit does a lot of heavy lifting when
it comes to externalizing the
characters' emotional experiences.
[music] Now, this sort of subjective
emotional framing is something that good
cinematography always does, but the
unique challenges posed by Wallace and
Gromit's silent characters really let
you understand [music] quite how
effective good cinematography can be for
creating understanding and empathy in an
audience. And nowhere is this more
impressive than with Feathers McGraw.
>> He is the most challenging element of
Vengeance Most Foul cuz he's so
graphically simple. He doesn't have any
form of performance other than a blink
and maybe the turn of a head. And you
know, when he walks, he just sort of
glides.
>> In many ways, Feathers McGraw is the
inverse of Gromit and that's largely
what makes him such [music] an effective
villain. Like Gromit, he's voiceless and
mouthless, but unlike Gromit, he has no
[music] brow and no visible pupils. And
so, while Gromit drives audience
connection through his emotional
transparency, Feathers prevents [music]
any such connection through his
emotional obscurity. We've already
spoken about the brow itself, but the
animation team also does a lot of their
emotional storytelling [music] through
the eyes of these characters.
>> We've got tiny pinholes in the eyes, so
all the animators have tools effectively
with [music] a pin on the end and we can
go in and make the tiny movements
required. We'll spend ages just looking
at the [music] eyes and how do you
convey when you're thinking about
something slightly sad? [music] And
we'll we'll figure out where his eyes
should be and how long they should stay
there before they flit across or
something. [music]
>> As humans, we're constantly trying to
infer intention, predict behavior, and
read emotional [music]
states from faces. But Feathers'
minimalistic design entirely suppresses
our [music] ability to do this and
because of that, he achieves something
reserved for only cinema's [music]
most interesting villains. He embodies
pure uncertainty and with it, pure
[music] discomfort.
>> That penguin, I think is one of the
great villains of all time. [music] It
was Hitchcockian.
You've never seen Hitchcock in clay
animation. Come on.
>> The restraint used around Feathers is
[music] what makes him fascinating. His
lack of facial expression, his stillness
[music] and rigidity. We're constantly
being forced to do a lot of cognitive
work in an attempt [music] to interpret
him and project intention onto him. And
as humans, when we're confronted [music]
with this sort of emotional ambiguity,
the thing we often project is [music]
threat.
That's the power of ambiguity in
storytelling. When used well, it makes
[music] our viewing experience an active
one. And in the case of Feathers McGraw,
it's one of the [music] things that
makes him the perfect foil to Wallace
and Gromit's emotionally expressive
world. He becomes not just a villain,
but their true emotional opposite, which
[music] is a powerful thing when it
comes to setting up a genuinely
memorable conflict. [music] But similar
to Gromit, it's not just the design and
animation style of Feathers [music] that
makes his presence so unsettling.
>> He actually becomes the most cinematic
character cuz you have to use music, you
have to use lighting, you have to use
the camera moves.
>> The music and cinematography [music] are
really the things that bring Feathers to
life. They're the components that truly
weaponize his stillness and create
[music] so much unease and power in his
small but sudden movements. For
instance, when he's first introduced,
it's really the music that cues the
sense of foreboding and mystery around
his character.
>> It's about the room, then. Well, that's
grand.
Um
would you like to come this way and it's
>> And later, it's music that turns his
simple movements like a sudden turn of
the head
into something sharper and more
threatening.
But it's the camera and lighting work
around Feathers that really [music] pull
everything together. Whenever Feathers
is on screen, the visual language
switches [music] to a film noir mode,
and shadows and techniques like Dutch
angles and dramatic push-ins are used to
dial up the sense of unease around him.
It's things like the slow push-ins, for
example, that work alongside his
inherent stillness and mechanical
blinking [music] to really bring out his
meticulous and calculating nature.
And then, there's the precision in
lighting him.
>> One of the things that kept him alive
the highlights in his eyes. If he turned
away from a key light and there was no
highlight, he switched off. And so, we
worked very hard with the camera team to
always have a highlight in his eyes even
if there wasn't a motivated light
source, they would cheat one in.
>> Catch lights, those little reflections
in our eyes that make them sparkle, are
something that we're always
subconsciously associating with live
thought and awareness, particularly in
art. In Feathers, [music] this tiny
detail is one of the most important
things in making him feel not just
alive, but intelligent, too.
>> [music]
>> In the end, it's the cinematography that
overcomes the challenge created by his
lack of pupils, elevating his character
by subtly shaping the idea of
consciousness within him. An illusion
crafted from almost nothing.
>> [music]
>> And that's what makes Wallace and Gromit
so special, the complexity and
intelligence in its emotional and
cinematic language. Every discipline,
every creative tool is used so
skillfully and deliberately to breathe
life into these clay puppets, creating
some of the greatest and most soulful
animation work we've ever seen.
Thank you, Nick Park, and thank you very
much for watching.
>> [music]
>> Cuz it's one thing being able to just
animate a puppet, make a puppet move
around the set in a vaguely human way,
but it's another thing making it seem
like the puppet has its own life and and
it's living and breathing and has has a
soul and a
>> That's the gold really, isn't it?
>> Yeah, yeah, that's the real skill.
>> Yeah.
>> [music and bell]
[music]
[bell]
[music and bell]
>> Hey.